Guide to Culinary Ephemera: Flour Products, Leavening Agents, and Baked Goods ams.0058
University of Michigan Library (Special Collections Research Center)
- Leavening Agents
  - Box 41.
    - Royal cook book. 49 p., 1930 (Box 41, Folder 11)
      Item [11] indicates that Royal Baking Powder is now part of Standard Brands, Inc. Format is similar to item [10], with revised content. Recipe for mince pie in [10] included making mince meat from scratch; this book only has baking directions. Newburg recipe calls for cooking sherry in place of sherry used in earlier editions. Has sample menus.
    - Royal cook book. 45 p., 1932 (Box 41, Folder 12)
      Item [12] has the same cover as [11], but inside cover now has advertisements for other Standard Brand products. Claims that the cookbook has been published since 1878. Contents revised from earlier editions. Includes discussion of ingredients for baking. Recipes call for sherry flavor or cooking sherry. Includes mailing envelope with NRA seal.
    - A guide to royal success in baking. 22 p, 1941 (Box 41, Folder 13)
      Item [13] states that Royal Baking Powder was introduced in 1866. Includes history of baking soda, baking powder, and cream of tartar. Chemical equations provided for cream of tartar baking soda. Inside cover quote "Today, with modern scientific bakeries in every community ... there is little necessity for the housewife to spend time on baking." Has judging and scoring standards for cakes. Detailed description of each step for butter cake.
    - 24 easy baking recipes your family will rave about made with new Royal S.A.S. phosphate baking powder. 16 p., 1944 (Box 41, Folder 14)
      Item [14] describes new Royal baking powder which contains no cream of tartar (sodium aluminum sulfate based). Has measuring instructions for those without graduated measuring spoons. Features Mary Woods of the Royal kitchens. Some recipes use margarine as alternative for shortening.
    - A guide to royal success in baking. 22 p. (2 copies), 1944 (Box 41, Folder 15)
      Item [15] is similar to [13], with unique cover art.
    - Royal cream of tartar cook book. 65 p., 1944 (Box 41, Folder 16)
      Item [16] has an illustration of Mary Woods on the cover. Noted as copyright 1940, revised edition copyright 1944. Has recipe for victory meat roll. Some recipes include wine or liquor as an ingredient.
    - Royal baker and pastry cook / by G. Rudmani. 44 p., 1888 (Box 41, Folder 17)
      Item [17] is similar to item [1], with unique art.
    - Special notice to the patrons of the Royal baking powder: [folded sheet], circa 1886 (Box 41, Folder 18)
      Item [18] is noted as a product insert. Has offer for free cookbook, also available in German on request.
    - Royal baker and pastry cook: a practical manual for every day cookery. 44 p., 1906 (Box 41, Folder 19)
      Item [19] is similar to item [4], with unique cover art.
    - Making biscuits: delicious recipes: biscuits, muffins, quick breads. 15 p., 1924 (Box 41, Folder 20)
      Item [20] is similar to item [9].
    - Royal cook book. 50 p. (2 copies), 1925 (Box 41, Folder 21)
      Item [21] is similar to item [10].
    - Royal cook book. 49 p., 1929 (Box 41, Folder 22)
      Item [22] is similar to item [11].
    - A guide to Royal success in baking. 22 p., 1939 (Box 41, Folder 23)
      Item [23] is similar to item [13].
    - Royal cook book. 64 p., 1939 (Box 41, Folder 24)
      Item [24] is similar to item [16], except no mention of Mary Woods.
    - Here are the cakes America loves-Royal cakes. 40 p., 1950 (Box 41, Folder 25)
      Item [25] has quote similar to item [13], except ends with "You need bake at home only when you wish ...". Reference to Mary Lynn Woods.
    - Do you know?: [recipe cards]., circa 1950s (Box 41, Folder 26)
      Item [26] contains loose items, each with a single recipe.
  - Box 42.
    Davis Baking Powder Company.
    H. D. Thatcher & Co.
    - The Crystal cook book: published in the interest of pure food / by Alice Priest Ewell. 127 p., 1905 (Box 42, Folder 1)
      Item [1] promotes "the pure food Crystal Baking Powder"; made with acid phosphate of soda. Has description of differences between other types of baking powder. Many recipes do not use baking powder as an ingredient. Theory of soup selection and economic value. Some recipes include wine or liquor as an ingredient. Invalid diet and household hints sections. Prices listed on inside back cover.
    - The cook's book. 63 p., 1909 (Box 42, Folder 2)
      Item [2] promotes K.C. Baking Powder, made from two unnamed acids (double acting). Recipes attributed to well known cooking experts (unnamed). Guaranteed to meet the food laws, both state and Federal. Illustrations of the products and factory. Some recipes include wine or liquor as an ingredient.
    - The cook's book. 63 p., 1911 (Box 42, Folder 3)
      Item [3] is similar to item [2] with fewer illustrations. Includes a recipe to make your own self-rising flour. Recipes are attributed to Mrs. Janet McKenzie Hill, editor "American cookery," but are similar to those in item [2]. Some recipes include wine as an ingredient.
    - Tempting Davis recipes. 20 p., 1925 (Box 42, Folder 4)
      Item [4] promotes Davis Baking Powder; a double acting product. Includes general rules for making quick breads. It has recipes for pumpkin pie and squash pie. Three pages of recipes for candy. Statement that every ingredient in their product is officially approved by U. S. food authorities. Indicates 47th year of production. Cover illustration is of period dress.
    - The Calumet baking book. New ed. 31 p., 1931 (Box 42, Folder 5)
      Item [5] promotes Calumet Baking Powder. Has a description of a test for double action in baking powder. Introduction by Marion Jane Parker. Cake recipe titles include number of eggs used.
    - A collation of cakes: yesterday and today / by Claudia Quigley Murphy. 31 p., 1923 (Box 42, Folder 6)
      Item [6] comes "through the courtesy of The Royal Baking Powder Co." for class rooms, women's clubs, etc. Includes bibliography. Historical recipes for cake and history of baking powder. Includes use of wine and liquor for flavor. Comments on benefits of cream of tartar based baking powder (like Royal) and problems with other types.
    - A lesson plan on Christmas suggestions / by Ruth Leone Rutledge. 18 p., 1925 (Box 42, Folder 7)
      Item [7] promotes Davis Baking Powder and "was prepared for teachers, demonstrators, and students of food and cookery." Cover inscribed: Nora Hughes. Has recipes for baked goods, candies, and salads. Poem: Now is the time of Christmas.
    - The little book of excellent recipes / by the mystery chef. 103 p., 1934 (Box 42, Folder 8)
      Item [8] promotes Davis Baking Powder. Scotch scone recipe gives direction for cooking on a griddle or in the oven. Beverages are made with Cocomalt. Includes household hints section. Seal of acceptance by the American Medical Assn. One chapter on national dishes of foreign countries. Includes main and side dish recipes as well as baked goods.
    - How to test baking powder, illustrated and explained. 24 p., 1894 (Box 42, Folder 9)
      Item [9] promotes Thatchers Sugar of Milk Baking Powder and includes the formula. Product is cream of tartar based. Edited by H.D. Thatcher, M.D. Other bases for baking powder described. Has illustrations of the company booth at the World's Columbian Exposition, 1893. Testimonials include name, address, and affiliation. Includes recipes with liquor as an ingredient. Back cover stamped: G.S. Mills, General Store, Hogansburg, N.Y.
    - Davis master pattern baking formulas. 80 p., 1940 (Box 42, Folder 10)
      Item [10] promotes Davis baking powder, Cocomalt, and Cut-Rite Waxed Paper. There are 21 master pattern baking formulas that serve as the basis for the 146 recipes. Color illustrations of finished products and methods are included. Some recipes have "more economical" versions following the conventional version. Has recipe for corn beef pasties. Incribed: H.A. Lewis.
    - Gold Label recipes. 17 p., circa 1910s (Box 42, Folder 11)
      Item [11] promotes Gold Label Baking Powder (notes that K.C. Baking Powder may be used). Every other page is blank.
    - The Calumet treasury of home baking. 24 p., 1971 (Box 42, Folder 12)
      Item [12] promotes Calumet Baking Powder and other General Foods products. Has recipes for monogram pancakes.
    - Fleishmann & Co.'s handy book for handy people: the young wife's friend. 32 p., circa 1890s (Box 42, Folder 13)
      Item [13] promotes Fleischmann & Co. Compressed Yeast. Includes verse "Learn to keep house." Exhibitable. Some recipes include liquor as an ingredient. Includes recipes for Zwiebel platz and Petersilien platz.
    - Northwestern Yeast Co.: [mailing envelope]. 1 p., circa 1920s (Box 42, Folder 14)
      Item [14] is a mailing envelope from Northwestern Yeast Co. with a three cent postage stamp.
    - Yeast bread and rolls / Lola T. Dudgeon, Mildred Dunn. 8 p., 1966 (Box 42, Folder 15)
      Item [15] is Cornell extension bulletin 888 from New York State College of Home Economics by Lola Dudgeon and Mildred Dunn.
  - Box 43.
    Wallace, Lily Haxworth.
    Pure Baking Powder Co.
    Jewett, Sherman & Co.
    Merchants Coffee and Spice Mills.
    Egg Baking Powder Co.
    - Table and kitchen: a compilation of approved cooking receipts. 57 p., 1907 (Box 43, Folder 1)
      Item [1] promotes Dr. Price's Cream Baking Powder (cream of tartar based). It includes tests for "adulterants" such as alum and ammonia. Has testimonials from chefs of major hotels. Some recipes use wine and liquor as ingredients. Cover note: 50 years the standard.
    - Table and kitchen. 57 p., 1908 (Box 43, Folder 2)
      Item [2] is similar to [1] with blue border on cover in place of cream. Does not include facsimilies of World's Fair medal (1892).
    - Table and kitchen. 57 p., 1913 (Box 43, Folder 3)
      Item [3] is similar to [1] with a plain front cover instead of color illustration. Has illustration of World's Fair medal. Refers to pure food laws. Ingredient fact sheet laid in. Back cover note: 60 years the standard.
    - Table and kitchen. 57 p., 1916 (Box 43, Folder 4)
      Item [4] is similar to [3]; with fact sheet bound in. Post Toasties leaflet from 1928 laid in. Blue label pasted on front cover advises that the number of eggs in a recipe can be replaced by adding more baking powder. Cover notes: manufactured by Royal Baking Powder Co.
    - Table and kitchen. 57 p., circa 1900s (Box 43, Folder 5)
      Item [5] is similar to [1]; back cover note: 40 years the standard. Has analysis of competing brands with name of product and manufacturer. Claims that the Army, Navy, and Indian Department of the US Government used 100,000 pounds of their product in the first five months of 1892.
    - Ryzon baking book / compiled and edited by Marion Harris Neil. 80 p., 1918 (Box 43, Folder 6)
      Item [6] promotes Ryzon, the perfect baking powder (mono-sodium phosphate based). Has list of prize winners with addresses, cooking schools, and names of judges. Notes on conserving eggs and wheat. Many recipes contain rice and corn flour. War used in titles of some recipes. Some recipes use wine or liquor as ingredients. Camp and open air recipes. Illustrations of hotels.
    - The Pure cook book / arranged and compiled by Gesine Lemcke. 126 p., 1904 (Box 43, Folder 7)
      Item [7] promotes Pure Baking Powder (cream of tartar based). The author is owner of the Greater New York Cooking School. Contains discussion of laws for ingredient labeling. Includes testimonials by chefs. Some recipes contain wine or liquor as an ingredient. Two pages of recipes in German. Advertisement for Keck's Gelatine, a powder made from pure calve's stock.
    - Jewette, Sherman & Co., manufacturers of White Lily baking powder ...: [folded brochure], circa 1890s (Box 43, Folder 8)
      Item [8] promotes White Lily Baking Powder (cream of tartar based). Some recipes measure flour by volume (quart or cup) and some by weight (pounds).
    - Egg baking powder. 31 p., circa 1905 (Box 43, Folder 9)
      Item [9] promotes Egg Baking Powder (egg white and wheat phosphate based). It has testimonials from chefs with illustrations of their hotel or restaurant. All Illustrations are line drawings. Printed on newsprint. One recipe includes wine as an ingredient.
    - Egg baking powder, New York. 31 p., circa 1910 (Box 43, Folder 10)
      Item [10] is similar to [9] but uses reproductions of photographs instead of line drawings and is printed on coated paper.
    - The Rumford cook book / by Fannie Merritt Farmer. 47, [1] p. "Some of the Medals awarded to ... Rumford Baking Powder ..." illustration on page [48]., circa 1895 (Box 43, Folder 11)
      Item [11] promotes Rumford Baking Powder (made from Professor E. N. Horsford's phosphate). Includes illustration of the factory and product packaging. Some recipes include wine or liquor as an ingredient. Newspaper recipe laid in. Marked B.22. Author was principal of Boston Cooking School.
    - The Rumford way of cookery and household economy. 68 p., circa 1912 (Box 43, Folder 12)
      Item [12] promotes Rumford Baking Powder. It was compiled by Janet McKenzie Hill with household hints by Mrs. Christine Frederick, household efficiency engineer. Chapter on table service has diagram and menu. Marked K.71. Includes offer for cook book.
    - Rumford dainties and household helps. 64 p., circa 1915 (Box 43, Folder 13)
      Item [13] promotes Rumford Baking Powder. Similar to [12], marked J.62. Includes offer for Rumford complete cook book by Lily Haxworth Wallace, National Training School of Cookery, London; free for 10 cards from product.
    - Little book of cakes and cookies. 15 p., circa 1919 (Box 43, Folder 14)
      Item [14] promotes Rumford Baking Powder. Includes offer for other Little books in series for one card from product. Marked U.86.
    - Salads. 16 p., circa 1919 (Box 43, Folder 15)
      Item [15] promotes Horsford's Acid Phosphate. In addition to baking recipes, several salad dressings include it as an ingredient. Marked D. 74. Includes offer for other bulletins: Good breads, meat substitutes, left-overs, and salads.
    - Cakes and cookies. 16 p., circa 1919 (Box 43, Folder 16)
      Item [16] is similar to item [15]. Offer includes same items as [15] and adds: cakes and cookies, delicious drinks, and dainty desserts. Marked X79 1 20.
    - Rumford book on home management. 64 p., circa 1920s (Box 43, Folder 17)
      Item [17] is similar to item [12] but compiled by Hannah Wing. Marked E.96. Has list of items required in the home and working heights for tables based on women's height. Has cleaning schedules, equipment, and supplies. Cuts of meat and their uses are described. Herbs and spices are described with their uses. Recipes to serve 100 included. Cook book offer on last page.
    - Rumford common sense cook book. 64 p., circa 1920s (Box 43, Folder 18)
      Item [18] is similar to item [13], marked Y-95. Has menus and suggestions for auto, picnic, and school lunch suggestions.
    - Rumford baking powder. [24] p., circa 1930s (Box 43, Folder 19)
      Item [19] is a small book of blank pages with handwritten recipes for cakes and icings.
    - 4 prize recipes: [recipe card]., circa 1930s (Box 43, Folder 20)
      Item [20] is a recipe card with three cake and one muffin recipes. Marked F.81. Describes a 48 page cook book.
    - 64 new uses for Rumford all-phosphate baking powder in daily cooking. 32 p., 1932 (Box 43, Folder 21)
      Item [21] is the 3rd ed. of the "new uses" series for their "all-phosphate" baking powder. Has discussion and recipes for using their baking powder in non-traditional ways, tested by Bertha M. Becker (section is reprinted from the previous ed.).
    - Rumford new use cook book. 32 p., 1935 (Box 43, Folder 22)
      Item [22] is the 4th ed. of the "new uses" series. Has history and an acceptance seal from the American Medical Assn. Has advertisement for Rumford Bakesall flour mix.
    - Captivating cookies. 16 p., 1941 (Box 43, Folder 23)
      Item [23] promotes the use of Rumford Baking Powder for making cookies. Introduction by Elizabeth Acru Baker.
    - Cakes to cheer about. 16 p., 1941 (Box 43, Folder 24)
      Item [24] is similar to [23], except the topic is cakes. Cover inscribed: Eileen Behrens.
    - Biscuits and biscuits glorified. 16 p., 1945 (Box 43, Folder 25)
      Item [25] is similar to [23], except the topic is biscuits.
    - Magic muffins! 15 p., 1945 (Box 43, Folder 26)
      Item [26] is similar to [23], except the topic is muffins. Includes order form for items [23], [24], [25], and [26] laid in.
    - Captivating cookies. 16 p., 1941 (Box 43, Folder 27)
      Item [27] is a later version of [23].
    - 90 Rumford recipes. 64 p., 1955 (Box 43, Folder 28)
      Item [28] promotes Rumford Baking Powder and includes recipes from items [23] through [26].
    - Rumford sugarless recipes: [folded brochure]., circa 1943 (Box 43, Folder 29)
      Item [29] promotes Rumford products. Cover art reflects World War II sugar shortages. Exhibitable.
    - Cake?: [folded brochure]., circa 1930s (Box 43, Folder 30)
      Item 30 promotes Rumford Baking Powder. Includes theory of cake ingredients and hints for correcting problems. Marked L-103.
  - Box 44.
    Kramer, Bertha F.
    Stevens, Carol.
    Golden Gate Compressed Yeast Company.
    National Yeast Co.
    Universal Foods Corporation.
    Red Star Yeast & Products Co.
    - Handy book for handy people: the young wife's friend. 30 p., circa 1900s (Box 44, Folder 1)
      Item [1] promotes Golden Gate Compressed Yeast. Some recipes contain liquor as an ingredient. Sample recipe titles: Queen of puddings, butterbarches, and Russian punch tart. Some information attributed to "Aunt Babette's" famous cookbook (Bertha Kramer, author).
    - National Yeast Co. cook book. 47 p., circa 1886 (Box 44, Folder 2)
      Item [2] promotes Vegetable Dry Hop Yeast for bread baking. Most recipes do not contain yeast. Some recipes include wine or liquor as an ingredient. Has illustration of the factory and period dress.
    - Magic Yeast recipes. 12 p., circa 1910s (Box 44, Folder 3)
      Item [3] promotes cake yeast. Illustrated recipes, packaging, and period dress. Packaging shows price of 5 cents. Recipe for root beer uses root beer extract.
    - Give them Magic Yeast bread: [folded brochure]., circa 1910s (Box 44, Folder 4)
      Item [4] promotes Magic brand cake yeast. Illustrations of packaging, finished products, and children in period dress.
    - Bake day suggestions: [folded brochure]., circa 1910s (Box 44, Folder 5)
      Item [5] contains three brochures similar to [4]. One copy has illustration of woman in period dress in the kitchen.
    - It's easy and economical: [folded brochure]., circa 1920s (Box 44, Folder 6)
      Item [6] is similar to [4]. Has coupon for free booklet: "The art of making bread." Advertisement for "Yeast foamers" weekly radio show on N.B.C. Blue Network.
    - You'll find a big difference: [folded brochure]., circa 1920s (Box 44, Folder 7)
      Item [7] is similar to [6]. Notes that Parker House roll dough can be kept in the ice box for several days.
    - The art of baking bread. 16 p., circa 1910s (Box 44, Folder 8)
      Item [8] promotes Yeast Foam and Magic Yeast. Has introduction wit discussion of elements of bread baking. Instructions on determining correct oven temperature without a thermometer. Mentions holding dough in an ice box. Period dress illustration on cover.
    - Your bread dough will be sweet and well leavened if you use Yeast Foam: [folded brochure]., circa 1910s (Box 44, Folder 9)
      Item [9] promotes Yeast Foam cake yeast. "Hannah L. Wesslins, formerly Bread Expert, Department of Agriculture, is head of our Home Economics Department." Offer for: "The art of baking bread," and "Dry yeast as an aid to health."
    - The art of making bread. 24 p., circa 1920s (Box 44, Folder 10)
      Item [10] promotes Yeast Foam and Magic Yeast ("... exactly the same except in name."). Tests and procedures for both hard and soft wheat flours. Fireless cooker recommended for proofing bread dough. Procedures for gas, oil, electric, coal, or wood stoves. Illustrated centerfold with steps to making bread. Back cover missing. Has street address of the company. Blue cover.
    - The art of making bread. 20 p., circa 1920s (Box 44, Folder 11)
      Item [11] is similar to [10], with less detail in instructions. No address for the company. Yellow cover.
    - The art of making bread. 25 p., circa 1920s (Box 44, Folder 12)
      Item [12] is similar to [10] with slight changes in wording and illustrations. Black cover.
    - Dry yeast as an aid to health. 12 p., 1923 (Box 44, Folder 13)
      Item [13] promotes Northwestern yeasts. Includes testimonials and descriptions of medical trials.
    - Eat Yeast Foam or Magic Yeast for health. 12 p., 1926 (Box 44, Folder 14)
      Item [14] is similar to [13]. Testimonials are attributed. Illustrations of period sports dress.
    - The art of making bread at home. 20 p., 1939 (Box 44, Folder 15)
      Item [15] promotes Maca; a fast, dry yeast that does not require refrigeration. Included portrait of Hannah L. Wessling. Illustrations of product packaging. Seal: Tested and approved, Good Housekeeping Bureau. Free copy to friends, on request.
    - Maca made. 32 p., 1939 (Box 44, Folder 16)
      Item [16] promotes Maca granulated yeast. Copies provided on request, with three wrappers. Recipes similar to [15].
    - The art of making bread. 29 p., circa 1920s (Box 44, Folder 17)
      Item [17] is similar to [10], no mention of fireless cookers. Recipes for fermented beverages are available on request. Blue with black cover.
    - Speed bake with the new quick method: [folded brochure]., circa 1930s (Box 44, Folder 18)
      Item [18] promotes the speed bake sponge process using potatoes. Instructions for hard or soft wheat flour.
    - New and easy recipes featuring breads and new ideas. 23 p., 1972 (Box 44, Folder 19)
      Item [19] promotes Red Star compressed and dry yeasts. Introduction by Carol Stevens. Includes general instructions and recipes. Has recipe for vintage fruit sauce with instructions for fermenting fruit. One recipe includes liquor as an ingredient. 2 copies.
    - 3 exciting new batter-way recipes: [folded brochure]., 1954 (Box 44, Folder 20)
      Item [20] promotes Red Star Yeast. Features a non-kneeded batter process for breads, rolls, and coffee cake.
  - Box 45.
    Fleishmann & Co.
    Fleishmann Company.
    - Choice recipes. 47 p., 1893 (Box 45, Folder 1)
      Item [1] promotes Fleischmann's compressed yeast for baking. Includes role of bread in health and activity, especially for girls and women, stating "It is no longer a sign of superior refinement for a woman to faint easily"--Preface. Some recipes include wine or liquor as an ingredient. Includes history of bread, instructions for bread making, and 12 general hints. Hint 12 is a test for moderately quick oven using a piece of white writing paper to check for browning or burning. Includes recipes for root beer, koumyss, and ginger beer. Two copies--one with page laid in before back cover marked: Form no. 607. Fleischmann's yellow label glued on p. 46.
    - Fleischmann & Co.'s jingles. Series no. 2. 1 v. (unpaged), circa 1898 (Box 45, Folder 2)
      Item [2] is second in Fleischmann's series of jingles, some incorporating Fleischmann's name. Includes bread recipe in rhyme. Illustration of "Largest Yeast Factory in the World, 10 acres, at Peekskill-on-the-Hudson." Fleischmann's yellow label on inside front cover. Two cents per cake.